Henry Ware Lawton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry Ware Lawton Papers 1849-1930 (bulk 1886-1902)
MSS29645
Lawton, Henry Ware, 1843-1899
1,900 items
6 containers plus 1 oversize
2.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Army officer. Correspondence, military papers, a map, photographs, printed matter, and miscellaneous material relating chiefly to Lawton's military career. Includes a copy of a journal of Esther Voorhees Hasson, 1899, and a copy of a diary of Leonard Wood, 1886.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Geronimo, 1829-1909.; Hasson, Esther Voorhees, 1867-1942. Esther Voorhees Hasson journal. 1899.; Lawton, Henry Ware, 1843-1899.; Lawton, Mary Craig, 1855-1934--Correspondence.; Naiche, approximately 1857-1921.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927. Leonard Wood diary. 1886.; Worcester, Dean C. (Dean Conant), 1866-1924--Correspondence.
Organizations
Relief (Hospital ship: AH); United States. Army.; United States. Philippine Commission (1900-1916)
Subjects
Chiricahua Indians--Wars.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Campaigns--Philippines.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Cuba.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Medical care.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Philippines.
Places
Luzon (Philippines)--History.; Philippines--Politics and government--1898-1935.
Occupations
Army officers.
Provenance
The papers of Henry Ware Lawton, army officer, were given to the Library of Congress by Louise Lawton Bagby in 1948 and by Oliver Bagby in 1964.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Library’s Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry Ware Lawton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1843, Mar. 17 Born, Manhattan, Ohio
1858 1861 Attended Fort Wayne Methodist Episcopal College (now Taylor University), Fort Wayne, Ind.
1861 Enlisted in the 9th Indiana Infantry (volunteers) Appointed first lieutenant, 30th Indiana Infantry (volunteers), and attained rank of brevet colonel by 1865
1864 1865 Commanded 30th Indiana Infantry in the Civil War; received Medal of Honor for gallantry at Atlanta, Ga.
1865 1867 Read law, law office of Judge Ninde, Fort Wayne, Ind., and attended Harvard Law School, Cambridge, Mass.
1867 Appointed second lieutenant, United States Army
1873 1888 Fought in Indian War campaigns (Sioux in 1876, Ute in 1879, Apache in 1886) with rank of captain
1881 Married Mary Craig
1886 Led army column that pursued Geronimo and his Chiricahua Apache warriors through the mountains of Arizona and Mexico and received his surrender
1898 Commanded 2nd Division, Army Corps in Cuba, during the Spanish-American War; participated in actions at Daiquiri, Siboney, El Caney, and Santiago de Cuba, and became military governor of Santiago de Cuba after the close of hostilities; held rank of colonel
1898 Accompanied President William McKinley on tour of the United States
1898 1899 Commanded 1st Division, VIII Army Corps in the Philippines, during the Philippine Insurrection, first as brigadier and later as major general of volunteers
1899, Dec. 19 Killed in action, San Mateo, Luzon, Philippines
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Henry Ware Lawton (1843-1899) span the years 1849-1930, with the bulk of the material dating from 1886 to 1902. The collection includes correspondence, military papers, a map, photographs, a copy of a journal of Esther Voorhees Hasson, 1899, a copy of a diary of Leonard Wood, 1886, printed matter, and miscellaneous material.
The correspondence relates primarily to Lawton’s army career and contains many letters from Lawton to his wife, Mary Lawton, describing his campaign against the Chiricahua band of Apache that resulted in the capture of Geronimo and Naiche (also known as Natchez) in 1886. Other topics include Lawton's life in the field in Cuba during the Spanish-American War, and the campaign on Luzon in the Philippines that led to his death. There is little correspondence reflecting his Civil War service or his many Indian campaigns before 1886. Included is a group of letters written to his wife after 1900 by Dean C. Worcester describing the Philippine Commission’s struggle and adjustment in governing the Philippine Islands. Also of interest is a copy of Esther Voorhees Hasson's journal from 1899 describing her experiences aboard the United States Army Hospital Ship Relief. The diary of Leonard Wood, who was selected by General Nelson A. Miles to be the medical officer on Captain Lawton’s command, describes the expedition against the Apaches in the Southwest.
The remainder of the collection is biographical in nature and enlarges on those aspects of Lawton’s life covered by the correspondence.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - General (Box 1)
    - 1849-1887, (14 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1888-1919, 1927-1930, undated, (10 folders) (Box 2)
  - Telegrams, undated (Box 2)
- Hasson, Esther Voorhees, copy of journal, 1899 (Box 2)
- Map, 1879 (Box 3)
- Military papers, 1861-1867, 1883-1900, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
- Miscellany, 1867-1928, undated (Box 3)
- Photographs, 1877-1910, undated (Box 3)
- Printed matter (Box 3)
  - Death of Lawton, 1899-1906 See also Oversize, (9 folders) (Box 3)
  - General, 1886, 1898-1914, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Indian campaigns, 1900, 1916 (Box 4)
  - Philippines, 1898-1899 See also Oversize, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 5)
    - 1886 (Box 5)
    - 1898 (Box 5)
    - 1899-1906 (Box 5)
  - Wood, Leonard, copy of diary, 1886, May 4-Sept. 27, (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Printed matter (Box OV 1)
    - Death of Lawton, 1899-1900, (Container 3) (Box OV 1)
    - Phillipines, 1899, (Container 4) (Box OV 1)